(classical music)
♪ Goodbye Cassini
♪ Your mission's fini
♪ Bravo Cassini
♪ Have some linguini
♪ You showed us Saturn's rings
♪ And lots of pretty things
♪ Huygens probe took
a dive early 2005 ♪
♪ Landed on Titan
it was exciting ♪
♪ Your mission never
failed to surprise ♪
♪ Dazzled our eyes now
♪ Dive to Saturn vaporize
(audience applauding)
(jet engines blasting)
- [Narrator] In 1997, an
ambitious international mission
launches to Saturn that
would, for the first time,
attempt to place an orbiting
spacecraft around the planet,
and land a probe on a moon
in the outer solar system.
But it was a mission
that had to fight its way
just to reach the launch pad.
- [Scientist] Our
Congress has had
some agony over the program.
We're gonna have
to operate under
a very strict fund ceiling,
and an unyielding schedule.
- [Scientist] We are all
gonna have to strive for,
as we go through this process,
is a continual search for the
least unacceptable solution.
- [Narrator] The journey to
Saturn took seven long years.
And being captured
into orbit depended on
what would happen
during just three hours.
- [Scientist] We
chased everything
that could go wrong
down the rabbit hole.
We went down every path of,
if this goes wrong,
what do we do?
If that that goes
wrong, what do we do?
- All stations on
net, SOI systems.
Just an advisory, we're
coming up on the time
that the critical
sequence will initiate
the turn to the
SOI burn attitude.
- [Scientist] This was
one of those moments where
you're either in orbit, or
you're a billion dollar fly by.
- Flight, SOI comm.
- [Flight Control]
Go ahead, SOI comm.
- The Doppler has flattened out.
(all cheering)
- [Narrator] With
Cassini safely in orbit,
science quickly
took center stage,
beginning with dazzling
images of Saturn's rings.
- [Linda] I'm surprised
at how surprised I am
at the beauty and the
clarity of these images.
They are shocking to me.
- [Narrator] Investigating
Saturn's iconic rings
will be just one part of
what will turn out to be
13 years of discoveries
about the Saturnian system.
And what will be realized
about Saturn's moons
will even transform how we
think about our solar system,
and open up new pathways
for the future of
space exploration.
- [Scientist] Around one planet,
we find two moons
that could potentially
have the key ingredients
to support life.
- [Narrator] "Triumph
at Saturn", next.
(contemplative music)
For some scientists, the
Saturnian moon, Titan
has been a higher
priority for exploration
than even Saturn,
or any other planet.
That's because
Titan may resemble
what Earth was like
billions of years ago,
making this moon a
kind of time machine
that preserves in deep freeze,
many of the conditions that
led to life on our planet.
Titan is the only moon
in our solar system
having a dense atmosphere,
made mostly of nitrogen,
just like the Earth.
There are smaller amounts
of methane and ethane
that break down into
organic compounds,
creating the moon's
smoggy orange haze.
Titan's extremely
cold temperatures
turn some gasses into liquids,
which led scientists to wonder,
could Titan have oceans,
made not of water, but of
liquid methane and ethane?
These questions made
the unmasking of Titan
a major objective of the
Cassini-Huygens mission.
And before the release
of the Huygens probe,
Cassini would have
the first opportunity
to see this moon close up.
With hope sky high
that the spacecraft
might see Titan's surface,
scientists were eager to share
the five hour plus flyby
live with the world.
- And you're watching
live coverage
from the Jet Propulsion
Laboratory in
Pasadena, California.
Tonight, the Cassini
spacecraft has its first
close encounter with
Saturn's largest
and most intriguing moon, Titan.
This is the closest we
have ever been to Titan.
And over the next
five and a half hours,
we hope to see the best images
we have ever seen of Titan.
And here on NASA TV, you
will see those images
just minutes after they
actually arrive on the ground.
- [Narrator] And, right on cue,
the images began streaming down.
But it quickly became apparent
that Titan wasn't ready
for its first closeup.
- We have just
received exciting word
that we have the first image in.
- [Carolyn] Okay,
so this looks like.
Boy, it takes a bit
of processing to
bring out features.
- [Narrator] What
appeared at first glance
to be black and white
smudges left scientists
and viewers alike puzzled
as to what they were seeing.
- [Carolyn] Look at
that, look at that.
And we don't know what it is.
- Anything stand out in
your mind at this point?
- Yeah, it's been a
very strange evening.
If you put me against
a wall and said
what's cloud and
what isn't cloud,
I really couldn't tell you.
I assume that much of
this is surface features.
Yeah, these are low contrast.
I'm not really sure what
we're looking at here.
- [Gay] With us now
is Torrance Johnson,
one of the imaging scientists to
kind of give us the
overall, what does it mean?
- Well, I think first off,
the main thing that
tonight's meant for us
is we've had a very
successful encounter.
We're really looking at a
great haul of data here.
And, well, you saw some
of the stuff coming in.
There's clearly stuff to be
seen there on that surface.
Understanding it's
a different issue.
And one of the things that
all of us on the project
have been talking
about for a long time,
is this sort of cooperative
science approach.
We knew Titan was
a tough target,
it was going to hold
its secrets tightly.
And so we designed this
mission, and the experiments,
to hit it with
everything we've got.
This is our first chance
to do that, really.
We're really gonna have to do
a full up complete body scan
of Titan to figure
out what's going on.
- [Narrator] This
encounter confirmed
that Titan would be as
complex as it was obscure.
Fortunately, there are many
more Cassini flybys still ahead.
But next up to explore Titan
is the European Space Agency's
Huygens Probe, that
will try to descend
all the way to the
moon's surface.
- The procedure here
is pretty standard.
We're gonna follow
right through the MOP.
The idea is a series
of brief reports.
- [Narrator] Eight
weeks have passed,
and it is the Eve of
Christmas Eve, as leaders of
the Cassini-Huygens team
hold a go, no-go meeting
on whether to release
the Huygens Probe.
- We had two opportunities
to update this,
one at the Titan's flyby.
- [Narrator] There are no known
technical issues with
which to contend,
making this meeting
mostly a formality.
- Navigation has flown
a precision trajectory.
So there was no need for
us to make any updates.
- Tracking data has been
absolutely excellent lately.
DSN is doing a really good job.
And Julie's team has
done a marvelous job.
She has given us recently,
really great news.
- Yeah, don't. Don't
jinx it, Jerry.
(all laughing)
- I'm just racing by.
There go the pagers.
- I know, yeah. As I jump,
'cause the pager goes off.
- Based on what we've heard here
from the representatives, and
the people that did the work,
it's very clear
that the orbiter,
JPL part of this team
is ready to proceed.
- The probe team is
also ready to go.
We are green for
tomorrow. So let's go.
- Okay, well let me just add
my enormous thanks from
the European side for the
terrific collaborative
effort on the US side.
It's just been great
to be working with you.
And I think we're all very
appreciative, and so let's go.
- Okay. We are a
go. You're good.
(all clapping)
- [Narrator] Southwood's
remarks were heartfelt,
as four years earlier,
the mission had faced
what seemed an
unsolvable problem,
a design flaw found
on Huygens' receiver
located on the
Cassini spacecraft.
An in-flight test
revealed the receiver
was incapable of adjusting
to Doppler shifts,
changes in radio frequencies.
That would leave Huygens'
data nearly worthless.
A major fix required
a hands-on solution,
impossible to do with the
probe a billion miles away.
Knowing little could
be done to Huygens,
the best hope
rested with Cassini.
When mission planners realized
that adjustments to the
spacecraft's trajectory
could minimize radio
frequency changes.
This required Cassini to
fly higher above Titan,
and at a relatively
slower speed, which
would allow the data
to be accurately recorded
as the probe descended.
But this solution was not free.
It would cost Cassini a
quarter of its reserve fuel.
This sacrifice confirmed
that Cassini-Huygens
was truly an
international partnership.
For without this decision,
Huygens was assured of being
seen as a failed mission.
The crisis was
now only a memory,
and it was now time for the
probe to detach from Cassini
to begin its dangerous
descent into Titan.
- [Julie] All station's are in.
Flight Director, we're
gonna do a final call here.
- [Narrator]
There's a JPL saying
that for some celestial reason,
major mission events always
seem to happen on holidays,
weekends, late at night, or
a combination of the three.
The probe's release is
no exception to the rule.
It is Christmas Eve.
- I'd like to start the
poll in five minutes.
- [Narrator] On hand
to show their support
for the Cassini team are
leaders of the Huygens probe,
JPL Director, Charles Elachi,
Caltech President,
David Baltimore.
And arriving just
in the nick of time,
JPL veteran, Tom Gavin,
whose job title includes
the phrase mission success.
- Nothing like cutting it close.
We already lost signal.
- Well, I knew you
had it under control.
(laughing)
- He came for when we
receive see the signal.
That's the important part.
- When will they acquire
signal, do you think?
- [Julie] Earliest
carrier lock is 7:29.
(dramatic music)
(voices overlapping)
(all cheering)
- Released, all three.
(all cheering and clapping)
- Okay, you're on your
own now, you know?
(high school band music)
- [Narrator] With the
Huygens probe now on its own,
silently free falling to
Titan for the next 21 days,
the Cassini team can relax
and enjoy the holidays,
especially New Year's Day.
That was because JPL
was sponsoring a float
in the Pasadena
Tournament of Roses Parade
for only the third time
in the lab's history.
The float featured
nine JPL missions.
The one at the top was Cassini.
(high school band
music continues)
(dramatic music)
The Huygens dive into Titan
is the most distant
landing ever attempted.
The descent through
the atmosphere
is expected to take
more than two hours.
The hope is that the
probe's batteries
will last long enough
to reach the surface.
What it will be like,
no one really knows.
Because there could be
lakes or seas of methane,
the probe has been
designed to float.
But first Huygens has to survive
the plunge through
Titan's atmosphere.
The entry speed is more
than 12,000 miles per hour.
Soon temperatures are soaring
over 3000 degrees Fahrenheit.
If the heat shield does its job,
the science instruments inside
the probe will have no idea
there is an inferno taking
place just inches away.
After surviving the initial
phase of the descent,
the first of three
parachutes deploys.
Nearer the surface, the
winds begin to calm,
and Titan's orange
haze begins to clear,
revealing below a
surreal landscape.
- So imagine descending
down through a misty,
cloudy atmosphere,
and suddenly below you
breaks this vista of
this very bright hill
with channels that
are carved by liquid,
with rounded pebbles
that were evidently
rolled and tumbled by liquid.
That was what the
Huygens probe saw.
And it showed us
that methane not only
is in the atmosphere,
but has been
raining and producing
weather, and carving features
in the landscape for
long periods of time.
(suspenseful music)
(loud crash)
- [Narrator] As Huygens
lands in a triumphant plop,
history is made.
And better yet, the probe's
batteries are still working.
What Huygens sees seems to
resemble a dried up riverbed.
Right in front are rocks
made of frozen water,
harder than stone.
There are no signs
of lakes or seas.
But Huygens view is
only a single spot
on a moon larger than
the planet Mercury.
The global reconnaissance
will come from Cassini.
On many of Cassini's
orbits around Saturn,
the spacecraft will
fly near Titan,
allowing navigators
to use the moon's mass
to alter trajectories,
while at the same
time, conserving fuel.
These flybys are also
opportunities to use
Cassini's powerful radar
to penetrate through
swaths of the moon's
hazy atmosphere.
The radio waves that bounce
back from Titan's surface
can be turned by scientists
into topographical maps.
Piece by piece, swath by
swath, Titan is revealed.
- Let's start at the
beginning and run to the end,
and just see what
interesting things we see.
And maybe you can point out the
things that you've seen too.
- [Carolyn] Okay.
Here is the new swath as
it comes through here.
- Titan really is, in some ways,
a kind of a cosmic
striptease act.
Because we can't
see the surface in
the normal wavelengths
that our eyes would use.
And the radar operates by
making images in narrow strips.
And so strip by strip
in different places,
Titan has been unveiled.
- [Carolyn] Here,
can everyone see?
- In that slide, you
can see a feature
that runs almost perpendicular
to the altimetry track.
- [Carolyn] So we see the
end of the dunes here.
Then you see the
dunes peter out.
And it gets brighter,
which is interesting, here.
- [Narrator] Massive dunes
are seen, made not of sand,
but of organic molecules
containing carbon.
- From the email
traffic last night,
I sorta gathered nobody
sees a magic island
in the data that
we have, correct?
- [Torrence] I think
that's correct.
- [Earl] Tell you what,
you all just zoom in on
the beginning of that.
- [Narrator] A large dark basin
turns out to be a
lake full of methane.
It is the first of
hundreds of deep lakes
and seas that will be found.
- [Scientist] Most of your
observation of this lake,
they show a top
surface reflection.
So the depth of this particular
lake is about 100 meters,
as we can see from
the axis of the image.
- Is it right to get out of
this that the small lakes
don't seem to be any shallower
than the larger lakes?
- [Narrator] Titan's
strangest discovery
is a continent sized
area named Xanadu.
Here are canyons and mountains
that resemble no other
place on this moon.
It is as if, one scientist
said, it's from another world.
- [Scientist] One thing,
just to make a quick
comment, is that
I am always very impressed
by the radar planning team.
They absolutely got it
right on the bullseye.
'Cause this is a long way away,
flying by at
kilometers per second.
And they put it right on
the bullseye. Nice job.
- [Narrator] Titan may
even have volcanoes
that gush out an icy mixture
of water and other materials.
And this water comes
from a hidden ocean
beneath Titan's icy shell.
And whenever water is mentioned,
it's not long before
the question is raised.
Is this a place that could
possibly support life?
- Giant Titan, the size
of the planet, Mercury,
has a global liquid water
ocean underneath its icy crust,
as well as methane lakes
and seas at the north pole.
And we wonder, could those
methane lakes and seas
support different kind of life?
So that's really
opened our eyes.
- [Narrator] There's still
more that was discovered.
This moon has
weather, and seasons.
Here it rains, not
water, but methane
that floats down like snow.
- It's so Earth-like, that
this is a very familiar place.
The chemistry in the atmosphere
is much more complex
than expected.
And the system as a whole is
just as intricate as Earth,
in terms of the atmosphere
interacting with the surface,
and the materials
on the surface.
Titan has a methane cycle,
just like Earth
has a water cycle.
And being able to
watch that in action,
seeing the lakes on the surface,
the channels that have been
carved into the surface,
and then actually seeing clouds
forming in the atmosphere,
and rain, the effect
of rain on the surface.
That whole cycle has
been one of the things
that's been absolutely
spectacular.
(calm music)
- [Narrator] Saturn's
moon, Enceladus,
was also a target of special
interest for Cassini.
It is the most reflective object
in the entire solar system.
And a great mystery
was why this moon
seemed to have so few craters.
Theories abounded.
Might there be some
internal heat source
that melts ice on the surface,
which then fills in the holes?
Could volcanoes or geysers
account for the
moon's shiny facade?
Or was Enceladus just a
dead, airless ball of ice?
Cassini would find the answer,
sending shock waves through
the scientific community,
all of it brought about
by one of the spacecraft's
least known science instruments,
the spacecraft's magnetometer.
It's a kind of high-tech compass
that makes measurements
of magnetic fields.
It's so sensitive that
it can even detect
the spacecraft's own
magnetic emissions.
To cancel out those
unwanted signals,
this instrument was marooned
out on the end of
Cassini's long boom.
On this flyby no
one was expecting
there would be much from
the lonely instrument.
- I must confess we weren't
expecting to see anything.
And so we didn't look at the
data for a couple of days.
And then when we went in
and looked at the data,
only magnetometer people
can get excited by our data.
'Cause you sort of
plotted on it on a scale
where you look at the whole day.
And we had to look at
the wiggles on the plot,
and they looked strange.
- The expectation was that
Saturn's magnetic field
would extend straight out,
and flow directly
through Enceladus.
Instead, the magnetic field
was curving around the moon.
There were also unexpected signs
of ionized water
vapor molecules.
These were measurements that
could be translated into sounds
as the spacecraft approached
and departed from Enceladus.
(high pitched whining)
- And so it was clear that
there was a source
of water group ions
in the vicinity of Enceladus.
And in addition to that,
there was something strange
going on in the magnetic field.
And it looked as if Enceladus
was a much bigger obstacle
to the flow of plasma and
field coming from Saturn.
It was almost as if the
magnetic field of Saturn,
and the plasma of Saturn
were being stood off
from the surface of the moon.
- [Narrator] Unsure of
the accuracy of the data,
Dougherty and her team awaited
the results of a
second, closer flyby.
- And I must confess. We looked
at that data straight away.
We were a little concerned about
the calibration
of the instrument.
But that there seemed to
be something in the data,
which was pointing
to an atmospheric
signature of some kind.
And at that stage,
we were talking about
an atmosphere covering
the entire surface.
- [Narrator] Not everyone
on Dougherty's team agreed.
For one thing, tiny Enceladus
lacks enough gravity
to hold an atmosphere in place.
In hopes of solving the
mystery, Dougherty proposed
flying even closer to
Enceladus on the next flyby.
Doing so would upset trajectory
and science plans
long ago mapped out,
but Dougherty's
argument won the day.
Navigators plotted out
a new course that sent
Cassini skimming just over
100 miles above the moon.
- For the couple of
nights before that flyby,
I didn't sleep.
What happened if we had
seen nothing at all?
No one would ever have
believed anything I said again.
And I didn't sleep well at all.
But then we got the data
back. And it was spectacular.
- [Narrator] In the
Southern polar region,
Cassini found the
landscape free of craters,
yet littered with house
sized boulders of ice,
carved out along
blueish trenches
that scientists dubbed
"tiger stripes".
The moon would no longer
be known for being smooth.
Here was a fractured surface,
containing crisscrossing
faults, folds, and ridges.
These crevices tell us
that Enceladus is
geologically alive.
(dramatic music)
From these fissures,
more than a mile deep,
geysers are erupting.
(geyser erupting)
Nicknamed Cold Faithful, they
are continuously spraying out
massive jets of ice
particles and water vapor.
(geysers continue erupting)
The speculation for more
than a decade before,
that the shiny
surface of Enceladus
might be the result
of ice vulcanism,
turned out to be true.
A momentous discovery
that began with unusual
wiggles on a chart.
- I thought, okay.
My reputation is saved. They're
not gonna think I'm crazy.
But also, it made
me feel really proud
of what magnetometer
instruments can do.
Because in some ways,
because we're just
wiggly data on a plot,
it's very hard to get
people enthused by our data.
You sorta media guys as well.
It's really difficult
to enthuse you.
- [Narrator] The detection
of geysers was stunning,
for it meant the
existence of liquid water
near the surface of
this bitterly cold moon.
And that turned
Enceladus, in an instant,
into a prime target for the
remainder of the mission.
Previous plans
were tossed aside,
in favor of adding
more Enceladus flybys,
including dramatic plunges
through the plumes.
(dramatic music)
- What is that?
And look at this little thing
here, this circular feature.
It's so complex.
The question is,
are both of them coming
out of the tiger stripes?
Be nice to get a temperature
measurement right on that.
Look at that. It looks
almost like a river.
But see that's in shadow,
but we can still see because
the moon is so bright.
But there's so much
multiple scattering.
- [Narrator] Enceladus is
as small as it is bright.
This small, when compared
to Earth and our moon.
Given its diminutive size,
it was thought Enceladus
would have long ago
lost any interior heat.
And what, scientists wondered,
was causing Enceladus' plumes
to spray out these hot spots?
The answer involves Saturn's
massive tidal forces.
They create friction
inside the moon's interior,
where there exists
an ocean of water,
a tremendous discovery.
And liquid from this
ocean Wells upward,
creating the moon's hotspots,
and the geysers that vent out.
And from these plumes,
scientists discovered
that the moon's
ocean contains salts
and complex organic molecules,
likely created by
hydrothermal vents,
the exact conditions
believed to have given rise
to life on Earth.
For many, these discoveries
about this tiny moon
was Cassini's biggest triumph.
For Enceladus is now one of
the most promising destinations
to search for life elsewhere
in our solar system.
Cassini's discoveries during
the first four years at Saturn
raised new questions to answer.
With the spacecraft
in excellent health,
NASA twice extended
the mission's funding.
Over the course of 13 years,
the spacecraft orbited
Saturn 294 times.
No two orbits were alike.
Determining the pathways
for these intricate loops
is the work of true
rocket scientists.
Or as they are called,
tour designers.
They are mathematical wizards
who charted courses through
the maze of Saturn's
80 plus moons and
its ring system.
- Tour should be
ranked green if it's-
- [Narrator] That
is half of the job
of these three tour designers.
The other half, trying
to please 200 scientists.
- This tour is
probably a yellow.
'Cause I hate to keep
having this email
exchange back and forth.
It looks bad, I think.
We're taking in all the
science requirements,
which are, you know, could
be a stack that thick.
We're kind of like a tour
guide bringing a big group
of kids, or scientists,
to Disneyland.
And the only problem is,
we have to stick
together as a group.
We all have to do
the same thing.
And it's again, trying to
please everyone equally,
or as my old supervisor
said, equally unhappy.
If everyone's equally
unhappy by the end
of the tour selection process,
then we've done our job.
- You can see that
all of the tours have
a large number of Southern
hemisphere coverage.
- We have evaluated the nominal
tours that came out last week.
Any modifications are things
that we're gonna have to
grapple with as a
group this week.
We can't have an input
that's a mix of the two,
unless we all understand
all of the implications.
- [Earl] Hey, guys. Can
I interrupt for a minute?
- They debate it out.
They listen to each other.
It gets heated at times.
- Is that a reasonable approach?
- [Candice] That's what I
would. I would like to say.
- But I have an objection.
Are we making the right
choice for the right reasons?
- Well, that's.
Every team is gonna have
to think about that.
Because we're not
gonna do the allocation
until after the
tour is selected.
So, in a sense you
are taking that risk.
- It can be very frustrating
at first because,
in one meeting someone say,
well do A, you gotta do A.
And in the next meeting they'll
say, oh, you can't do that.
You have to do this instead.
- Just a strategic comment.
I think everybody in this
room knows how rushed
the evaluations
for all these were,
because they came in so late.
- It starts out everybody's
on different ends,
sometimes yelling, sometimes
red faced, really mad.
Like they're really trying
to make sure they get heard.
- The tour designers
have been looking at
what is the flexibility,
in a given tour to raise
and lower the altitude?
We have to look at
the ripple effect.
- When you're up high,
out of the orbit plane,
you're up way above Saturn,
you get a good
view of the rings.
But you're not around
any of the other moons.
And so the people that
want to look at the rings
want to be up high,
and look at the rings.
The other people want to be down
in the same plane
with the rings,
where they can visit
all the other moons.
And that's a huge tug of war.
You know, it's such that the
JQ perturbations are maximized.
- [Scientist] What
you're hearing here,
and I said it earlier,
what are you hearing
from people in this room.
They haven't had
a chance to really
evaluate the
information in a way,
well enough so they think
we've got the right decision.
So I think-
- We had went through
the stressful times
earlier in the week,
meeting with each discipline
working group, 'cause
we sit in front of these,
40 or 50 world renowned
scientists in a specific field.
And it's kind of like a
Congressional hearing,
where they just fire off
questions one after the other.
And you really have
to know your stuff,
and understand every
idiosyncrasy of
each specific tour.
- But after they
got heard, I mean,
people kind of calmed
down a little bit.
But eventually
everybody agrees, yeah,
that's kind of the best thing.
So we're very lucky
that the spacecraft
is very highly functional,
and we have a lot of fuel.
All the tours are good.
And I'd feel happy if
any of them got selected.
I mean, all of them are
gonna be really exciting.
I mean, just. I mean,
just amazing pictures.
It's almost like
we have Ansel Adams
riding on the spacecraft.
I'm talking about
pictures, but I mean
the other stuff is neat too.
I mean, some of
these instruments,
they can just take a picture.
And they can tell you
what it's made out of.
It's like some sort
of Star Trek thing.
But really, Star Trek didn't
have instruments this cool.
They just had this green ray.
And it did everything, right?
They're tri-corder or whatever.
Or they really amazing stuff,
is when they find stuff it's
like, they have no idea.
Like, Iapetus, that ridge.
Iapetus, it's like the
equator actually is marked.
When I was a kid, I had a
globe that got messed up,
and the equator
kind of stuck out.
I mean that's the
way Iapetus is.
There's this mountain ridge
right along the equator.
It's so bizarre.
- [Narrator] This
meeting was only one
of several taking place.
It is at this larger gathering
where the proposals
of the tour designers,
representing a year's worth
of work with little time off
for weekends and
holidays, will be judged.
- Compared to the usual agenda,
today is turned upside down.
And the reason for that is,
tour design is the main
topic of this whole meeting.
You'll notice that there's
some filming or video going on.
This is a JPL activity
to document how
decisions are made on projects.
(laughing)
And, well they're gonna have
a cutting and editing process.
So I'm not sure that we'll
recognize it necessarily.
In any case-
- It's like the worst
take-home final ever invented.
You have 200 professors,
and the hardest questions
you can think of.
And you're just kind
of slogging through it,
trying to get it done,
and then you hand it in.
PF7, 11, they're both very
much like six and 6H9.
It kind of feels good
to have it handed in,
but you're not
really awake enough
for really much of
emotion or anything.
So you end up with a
Titan flyby at apple axis,
or at periapsis, and
then you come back.
Then you do a pie transfer,
then you crank up again.
So there's a lot of
inclined time in this.
And when it comes down-
- [Narrator] From an infinite
number of possibilities,
the tours are
whittled down to nine.
Next, the science
teams are to rank them
as green, acceptable,
yellow, partially acceptable,
or red, not acceptable.
- [Scientist] But it
sounds like 6H9 and eight
should either both be, both
be red or both be yellow.
- [Narrator] But wanting
more wiggle room,
scientists introduce a new
color to the voting, lime.
- [Scientist] Okay.
6H9, three greens,
a lime, and a red.
- [Nathan] I mean, it's
kinda like our job was,
oh we were just waiting
to hear the result.
I mean, I guess it's kinda
like the jury coming in,
but you're too tired to
care what your sentence is.
- So you're talking
about PF9 for Titan?
- [Narrator] Eventually
a consensus is reached.
(audience applauding)
No doubt, the winning tour
has left the scientists
equally happy and unhappy.
The tour designers
are just plain happy.
For the first time in a year,
they will have their lives back.
- It's done. It's over.
The decision's been made.
We were happy, but
also just absolutely
felt like a truck
had run over you.
(light hearted music)
(dramatic music)
- Hello, this is Arthur Clarke
joining you from my home
in Colombo, Sri Lanka.
I am delighted to be
part of this event
to mark Cassini's
flyby of Iapetus.
- [Narrator] When
science fiction writer,
Arthur C. Clark
wrote the classic,
"2001: A Space Odyssey",
he chose for the book's final
scene, Saturn's moon Iapetus.
- As you know,
I have more than a passing
interest in Saturn.
- [Narrator] In the
movie version of "2001",
the ending scene was
changed to Jupiter.
But for Clark, Iapetus remained
a place of deep mystery.
He shared his enthusiasm for
Saturn's third largest moon
with those who gathered
in JPL's auditorium
to witness images of Iapetus
as they first arrived.
- This is a particularly
exciting moment
for fans of "2001:
A Space Oddysey".
Because that's where the
lone astronaut, Dave Bowman
discovers the Saturn monolith,
which turns out to be
a gateway to the stars.
More than 40 years later,
I can't remember why
I placed the Saturn
monolith on Iapetus.
But I've always had this
strange fascination with Saturn,
and its family of moons.
By the way,
that family has been growing
at a very impressive rate.
When Cassini was launched,
we knew of only 18 moons.
I understand there's
now 60, and counting.
I can't resist the
temptation to say,
my God it's full of moons.
So I'm going to keep
my fingers crossed
for what Cassini
discovers at Iapetus.
I want to thank everyone
associated with this mission.
Science projects are
tremendously important
for understanding
of the solar system.
Who knows?
One day, our survival on Earth
may depend on what we
discover out there.
This is Arthur Clarke, wishing
you a successful flyby.
(audience applauding)
- [Narrator] What Cassini saw
at Iapetus was breathtaking.
Many of the observations
focused on examining
a mountain ridge on the equator
that contributes to the moon's
unusual walnut
shaped appearance.
These mountains,
made mostly of ice,
are among the tallest
in the solar system,
soaring 12 miles high,
more than twice that
of Mount Everest.
Scientists have
more than one idea
as to how they may have formed.
- One thought is that perhaps
when Iapetus was more
fluid or pliable,
it was spinning very, very fast.
So it sort of bulged out at
its equator as it was spinning.
And as it cooled off,
then it held that shape,
actually had that mountain
range going around it.
- [Narrator] While the
bulge remains to be solved,
scientists believe they
are on more solid ground
as to the reason why Iapetus
is so starkly black and white.
- One of the puzzles going all
the way back to Voyager is,
is that dark material
coming from inside Iapetus?
Maybe some kind of
volcanic eruption?
Or is it coming from outside?
And Cassini solved that puzzle.
Turns out that there's
a captured moon, Phoebe,
in the outer part of
the Saturn system.
Dust from Phoebe comes
in, and gets swept up
onto one side of Iapetus,
coating that side in almost
a charcoal black material.
- [Narrator] This black material
absorbs heat from the sun,
turning the moon's
water ice into a vapor
that accumulates like snow
falling on the trailing
side of Iapetus.
The result is the moon's
distinct yin and yang veneer.
Phoebe, the moon responsible
for Iapetus's dark material,
resides on the outskirts
of the Saturnian system.
This is a frozen
artifact from the time
when the solar
system was forming.
Its battered surface
speaks of a violent past.
Everywhere there are ancient
craters, and landslides.
Phoebe was the first Saturnian
moon Cassini saw up close.
And it proved to be a harbinger
of the bounty to come.
For at the time of
Cassini's launch,
there were just 18
confirmed Saturnian moons.
Now there are 82.
These moons are as
diverse in shape,
size, and composition,
as they are numerous.
Battered Mimas, with
its massive crater,
resembles the Death
Star from "Star Wars".
Hyperion resembles a sponge.
Its interior is full of voids,
so much so that it's thought of
more as a rubble pile
than a solid body.
Atlas could be
mistaken for a UFO.
Prometheus, a potato.
And Pan, a ravioli.
These and other moons are part
of Saturn's intricate system
that influences the
rings, the magnetosphere,
and even the planet.
And while best
known for its rings,
Saturn is deserving
of its own attention.
It is the second largest
planet in the solar system.
In volume, Saturn could
hold more than 700 Earths.
Composed mostly of helium
and hydrogen gases,
the planet has no solid surface.
Although deep within
there is thought to be
a dense core of metals.
Despite its size, Saturn
is astonishingly light,
less dense than water.
If it could be placed in
an imaginary giant bathtub,
Saturn would float.
The planet's spin rate
is also impressive.
The Saturn day is only
10 and a half hours long.
This rapid rotation
causes the planet
to bulge out at the equator,
and flatten at the poles.
Saturn's butterscotch exterior
appears bland and calm.
But this appearance
is deceiving.
Beneath the cloud tops is a
churning cauldron of lightning,
and wind speeds that can
reach over 1000 miles an hour.
At about every 30 Earth years,
Saturn experiences a mega storm.
(dramatic music)
Cassini had the good
timing to witness one.
This raging storm would grow
to encircle the entire planet.
(thunder rolling and
lightening crashing)
Even more amazing is what can
be seen at Saturn's poles.
- Saturn has something
unique in the solar system.
It has a hexagon
circling the north pole.
It's a six sided jet stream.
You could almost imagine
horses on a race track
racing around the hexagon.
We don't know why it
keeps its six sided shape.
It's some kind of a wave
pattern that goes around Saturn.
But it's very stable. It's
been there for decades.
It's about two Earth
diameters across.
At the very center,
right at the north pole,
there's a giant hurricane.
It's about half the size of
the Continental United States,
with wind speeds
about four times
a typical hurricane force wind.
- [Narrator] A
second monster storm
was discovered at
Saturn's south pole.
It is also ringed with towering
clouds, but lacks a hexagon.
And while this vortex
looks like a hurricane,
it doesn't behave like one.
These are just some of
the wonders of Saturn
witnessed by Cassini.
But still to come is an
entirely different way
to explore the planet, as
the spacecraft nears its end.
By 2017, Cassini had circled
Saturn more than 250 times.
The mission's achievements
had earned the praise of many,
including the first
human ever to set foot
on another celestial body.
- Hi, I'm Neil Armstrong.
We're here at the
Cincinnati Observatory.
- [Narrator] Armstrong
recorded this message
to the Cassini team four
years before his passing.
- It has been said,
science is about what is,
and engineering is
about what can BE.
The Cassini-Huygens program has
demonstrated the best of both.
And you are the people who
made it the enormous success
that it has been, and is.
Some of you are in
science of what is,
unraveling the secrets
of the Saturnian system.
Someone's had a full-time
job just counting moons.
The number of your
new discoveries
is nothing short of amazing.
Some of you were in the
what can be category.
You were involved in the
design of the spacecraft,
and the trajectories,
system design and operation,
instrumentation, how to
make the measurements,
programming the computers.
We all give you our
very best wishes
to continue your
outstanding performance.
Congratulations to each
and every one of you.
- [Narrator] Cassini's
original lifetime warranty
was for four years at Saturn.
The mission more than
doubled that guarantee.
In 2017, 20 years
after its launch,
the spacecraft was still
performing beyond expectations.
- It's like the spacecraft
just now broke in.
Everything's working
just perfectly.
- [Narrator] Yet Cassini's
days are now numbered.
It is running out of fuel.
And before that happens, the
spacecraft has to be sent
on a course that will
ensure it will not crash
into one of Saturn's moons
that might harbor life.
- Given that Enceladus
now appears to have
all the ingredients
that could harbor life,
we have new rules.
And frankly we have a very
nice home for microbes.
It's room temperature
inside a spacecraft.
A hardy microbe could easily
have hitched a ride along.
We went through
a lot of studies on disposal
options for the spacecraft.
Some of them were to take it
into very long looping
orbits of Saturn,
where it would be stable
for thousands of years.
But the scientific
benefit wasn't there.
We also had options
to go back to Jupiter,
go out to Uranus, go to
the Trojan asteroids.
We could have exercised
a lot of those options,
but none of them had
the strength and appeal
of a scientific
mission at Saturn.
We were built for Saturn.
Saturn was absolutely
just bristling
with things we
hadn't yet explored.
Once we chose to stay,
we had to figure out
how to dispose of the
spacecraft cleanly.
- [Narrator] It's decided
to end the mission
by plunging Cassini into Saturn.
But not before attempting
to dive 22 times
between the planet
and the rings,
a place no spacecraft
has ever been.
(light hearted music)
- So this is where
Cassini is right now
in its orbit of Saturn,
below the ring plane.
It goes out here, will come
over the top of the rings again,
in a few days.
We do this every
seven and a half days.
On April 22nd,
spacecraft will
fly fairly close to
Saturn's big moon, Titan.
And Titan has enough gravitation
that we can use it to trade
orbital momentum between
Titan going around Saturn,
and the spacecraft
going around Saturn.
And with that trade off,
a marvelous thing happens.
The orbit of the spacecraft
jumps inward towards Saturn,
so that the next
close fly by of Saturn
will be in between the rings
and Saturn's atmosphere.
Is that dangerous?
We don't really
know, but who knows?
We might run into some big
ring particles in there
that we can't see
in our observations.
If that happens, oh well,
it's been a good mission.
If it doesn't clobber the
spacecraft right away,
then we'll have 22
more flights through
all the way out a million miles.
It's a million mile
high roller coaster.
Picture yourself
going click, click,
click, click, click up
a huge roller coaster.
And then starting in,
it's just falling.
As we whip through the space
between the rings and planet,
we'll be going 120,000
kilometers per hour.
(suspenseful music)
(jet engine roaring)
The most important
thing, I think,
is the moment when Cassini's
signal reaches the Earth.
That means that the
spacecraft has gone through,
I don't know, maybe
1000 different commands,
turning the spacecraft,
operating the cameras
and spectrometers,
and dust detectors
and magnetometer.
They make their observation.
Spacecraft keeps turning and
twisting to point everything.
And the moment the
signal hits Earth,
we know that all of
that, in the past day,
has been successful.
And I think that's party time.
- [Narrator] But before
there can be party time,
there's the less glamorous work
of creating those commands,
and sometimes testing
them in tucked away labs.
- I think we're good to go.
- Are we alert?
- Well, this is
another seed kernel.
So after this meeting,
I'm gonna have to switch out
this seed kernel for 467.
This is 444, right.
- Running real time.
'Cause it's synced up
to real space time.
So we just want to leave
it sitting right there.
Kind of a reminder
of when the first.
- Right.
So the first ACS
command is at 10:52:38.
Yeah, yeah.
- What we're setting up is,
we're practicing a
main engine maneuver
we could need in the last
few weeks of the mission.
So to either come up
out of the atmosphere,
or go down into the atmosphere.
So actually we're
just simulating
about a one meter per
second main engine burn.
So the engine's gonna
burn for how many seconds?
- I'm not sure.
- Four or five seconds?
- Do you remember?
- Joanie?
- Joanie, how long does the
burn last, on one meter?
- About six seconds.
- Six, okay.
So what the spacecraft does,
is the spacecraft always
starts from Earth point.
And it does a roll and
then it does a yaw.
And then you'll unyaw,
and then unwind, and
come back to Earth point,
and then relay all the
data back down to Earth.
We'll be able to, because we're
in the integrated test lab,
we'll be able to see all
the data in real time.
So we're actually gonna
call it out in real time,
since we're practicing it.
- [Interviewer]
What is a SWAMBO?
(laughing)
- It stands for She Who Always
Must Be Obeyed. (laughing)
- It should take
about 29 minutes.
- So here it is.
And they're calling
something out right now?
- Systems?
- [Luis] Systems.
- Go ahead.
- The wind roll
turn is complete.
- The reaction wheels
have powered off.
- [Luis] There it is.
- Here we go.
Hey, Attitude Control.
- [Joanie] You
weren't listening.
- I wasn't listening?
- They said it.
Tina called it out.
- Tina, I can't hear you.
- [Tina] I'm sorry.
- You and Masashi are
gonna have to speak up.
You're gonna have to
develop your Julie voice.
- She was literally
just saying the words,
"Oh, I have to announce",
when you said "Call
out the burn status".
(all laughing)
(voices overlapping)
- [Narrator] It is now
more than a month later.
All of the testing
of commands is over.
And on this evening,
team members
and their families and
friends have gathered to see
if Cassini will survive
its first plunge
between the rings and Saturn.
The event has been given a name,
Gateway to the Grand Finale.
- Well, I just want to
welcome everyone to our
gateway to Cassini's
Grand Finale.
And this is a
Cassini family event.
And I'm so happy to
see so many people here
to share in what's
about to happen tonight.
- [Narrator] In
1990, Linda Spilker
stood on this same stage
speaking of Saturn's rings.
- Saturn's rings are
more transitory elements-
- [Narrator] Now,
three decades later,
she is Cassini's
project scientist,
and this evening's
master of ceremonies.
- So at midnight tonight,
will be the first time Cassini
turns back to the Earth,
sends a signal, and lets us know
that it successfully
navigated through
this gap where it's flown for
the very, very first time.
So we have a lot in store.
It'll be very exciting.
- [Narrator] While
awaiting news at midnight,
updates are given on Cassini's
latest science discoveries.
And a time honored JPL
ritual is acknowledged.
- Now, I'm not
particularly superstitious.
But you know there's a long
standing JPL tradition.
So last night, I went
out and I decided
we needed to have some
lucky peanuts, just in case.
And I thought about it
some more and I thought,
maybe we need two jars (audience
laughing) of lucky peanuts.
And with that,
I'd like to introduce the
Cassini Virtual Singers.
The Virtual Singers
really take the heart
and the soul of Cassini,
and capture it with music.
So tonight, live from JPL
in Pasadena, California,
just back from their
multi world tour.
(audience laughing)
We now have the Cassini
Virtual Singers.
(audience applauding)
♪ Cassini flies over the ocean
♪ Cassini flies over the sea
♪ Cassini flies through
the ring plane ♪
♪ Oh send back good data to me
♪ Send back oh send back
♪ Send back good
data to me to me ♪
♪ Send back oh send back
♪ Send back good data to me
♪ Send back good
data to me to me ♪
♪ Send back oh send back
♪ Send back good data to me
(audience applauding)
- [Narrator] As the Cassini
Singers take their bows,
flight team members slip away
to take up their positions on
console in Mission Control.
- [Molly] I read
you, five by also.
Power, voice check on FSO chord.
- [Scientist] I read
you five by five.
- [Molly] I ready
you five by also.
- [Scientist] 10-4.
(voices overlapping)
- [Scientist] I read
you, five by five.
- I read you, five by also.
Flight Director,
I'm Project Manager.
I'd like to announce
at this time
that all stations
are ready to support.
- [Scientist] Copy you.
- [Scientist] Copy
that, thank you.
(dramatic music)
- Okay, what we're
looking at here
is the Mission Support Area.
And they each have
their various stations
looking at different
aspects of the spacecraft.
And they just went through
a check to make sure
that everyone can hear
everyone else in the MSA.
And we also have sound
into that room as well.
So Erick, do you
want to talk about
what we're seeing on
the screen over here?
- Yeah, so on the left,
that is the signal that
Deep Space Network is currently
detecting, which is nothing.
It's just a flat noise
signal right now.
But what we're all going
to be looking for here is
for a spike to pop
up out of that noise.
And when we see that spike,
it means that we're receiving
a signal from Cassini.
- We have excellent
carrier signal detection
in the auto loop receiver.
(all clapping)
(audience applauding)
- That's a nice booming signal.
So the carrier signal is there.
We'll have to wait a few
more minutes until that,
we'll see if there's
actual data flowing.
But this is a great sign.
- [Narrator] Receiving
back Cassini's carrier tone
means the spacecraft has
survived the first dive.
- Signal just came booming
through right on time.
Couldn't have been better.
- [Narrator] Along
with feelings of relief
is the hope that science
data will soon begin to flow.
But now comes a
moment of confusion,
how to best listen
for Cassini's signal.
- [Ace] Esco
Systems, Cassini Ace.
The station is
currently looking for
the X band one-way
carrier signal.
They're also gonna attempt
to lock up to the AT99-6.
So stand bye, one. I'll
let you if they get it.
- Ace, this is Flight Director.
Don't have them lock
up on the AT99-6.
- [Ace] Okay, you just want
them to look for carrier?
Esco Systems, Cassini Ace.
The station has locked up
to the X band one-way signal
at neg 140DB, which is
expected for the AT99-6.
- That's not good. No.
- [Esco Systems] Copy.
- [Nave] Esco
Systems, this is Nav.
- [Esco Systems] Nav, go ahead.
- [Nav] We're seeing a
one- way Doppler signature.
- [Esco Systems] Copy.
- [Narrator] The
moment of uncertainty
ends as quickly as it began.
And Cassini begins transmitting
its science data
sooner than expected.
- Flight Director on net.
Well, we were waiting for 12:05,
but it looks like we're early.
(all cheering and clapping)
(audience applauding)
- Oh my God.
- Well, if there's
any more questions,
I'd be happy to take questions.
I mean, this is the big
moment that we waited for.
And it's here, and it's every
bit as good as we had hoped.
- We're okay for 22 weeks.
We're okay now.
- The spacecraft went
through the ring plane
just clean as can be.
There were no indications
of fault protection.
Telemetry data playback
is exactly where
it's supposed to be.
We can all go home.
We don't want to spend all
night fixing everything up.
The spacecraft's
in perfect shape.
- [AECS] System
lead, this is AECS.
- [System Lead] AECS, go ahead.
- The downlink roll has started.
At this time, we
would like to report
that all the initial
conditions checked out.
Initial attitude and
wheel speeds look good.
All instruments are on.
The star tracker is tracking
five stars, so that looks good.
Both sun sensors, A
and B, are both on.
So they match each
other's telemetry.
At this time, we're
waiting for the roll
to give us a full
quadrant checkout
for the rest of the pass.
Other than that,
AECS looks great.
- Copy.
Flight Director, and Project
Manager. This is Systems Lead.
All subsystems have reported in
including the sip
lead at this time.
And everything is nominal.
- [Earl] Congratulations,
everyone.
(all clapping)
(grand music)
- Hello, everyone. I'm
Gay Yee Hill and welcome
to NASA's Jet
Propulsion Laboratory.
After two decades in space,
NASA's Cassini
spacecraft reached
the end of its remarkable
journey of exploration.
Today, the spacecraft made
its final approach
to the giant planet,
and plunged into the
Saturn's upper atmosphere,
ending this
extraordinary mission.
But due to the vast
distance between Earth-
- [Narrator] The Cassini
mission has actually not ended.
Not yet.
The grand finale event
is still a week away.
This is a rehearsal.
- The sun isn't up
yet, and more than 1500
Cassini scientists,
engineers, alumni,
their friends and family,
have gathered in
Mission Control here,
Von Karman Auditorium at JPL,
Beckman Auditorium at Calgary-
- [Narrator] What's
true for engineers
is also true for JPL's
public communications team.
A little pre-planning
to work out the kinks
can be worth its weight in gold.
- In Australia.
It's 4:00 am here in California.
The loss of signal
really happens
at about 3:30 Pacific
time, a half hour ago.
Why is the team here?
- We thought it'd be over.
- We will be checking
back with you
in just a couple more minutes.
There is a huge crowd
at Beckman Auditorium
at Caltech right now.
Cassini science team member,
Morgan Cable, is there.
Morgan, what is
it like out there?
- Hi, Gay.
This is Morgan here at Caltech,
and the atmosphere is electric.
- I believe we're
going to a bumper.
- And I am one of those
hoping that Cassini will
hang in there and fight for
the very last seconds of data.
- What's going on?
- Well, we've just got
the word that Cassini has
given us its last bit of data.
The room is celebrating.
Lots of hugs going
on, a few tears.
- With me now is NASA Director
of Planetary Science, Jim Green.
Jim, thanks for joining us.
- You know, Gay, this really
has been a historic mission.
- Before we do that, let's
take a moment to chat
with JPL Director, Mike Watkins.
What's your feeling about
the success of the
Cassini mission?
- I could not be more proud
about the role that we've
had in this mission.
- With me now is
Alvaro Genannez,
the ESA Director,
and the Director of
Science, Roberto,
ESA Director of Science,
Roberto Battiston.
Battiston, Battiston.
- Baggett Battiston.
(laughing)
- [Narrator] But
all kidding aside,
the planning paid off.
For the elaborate multimedia
and interactive coverage
of Cassini's Grand Finale
would be watched by millions.
- And the Emmy goes to,
NASA JPL, "Cassini's
Grand Finale".
- [Narrator] And earned
JPL its first ever Emmy.
- I got to thank the
stars that that made
a bunch of geeky
rocket scientists,
rocket engineers and
scientists, into rock stars.
(camera clicks)
(audience cheering)
- [Jonathan] Here's the
Huygens image of the gulley-
- [Narrator] Less than a week
remains before Cassini's end.
And team members from around
the world are arriving
to take part in
the Grand Finale.
This is the final meeting
of the science radar group.
- We've actually been
at this for 40 years.
This is an image from 1976.
It's one of Bruce Murray's
purple pigeon projects.
And here's what became
the Huygens probe,
beaming the data to
Cassini, which is flying by.
That far in time, I
want to make a caveat.
- [Narrator] As they meet,
a billion miles away,
Cassini is flying by
Titan for the last time.
- Right now, Cassini is
flying close to Titan,
74,000 miles away.
And Titan's gravity has
given Cassini its final push,
its goodbye kiss, and
its fate is sealed.
And toast to a great
spacecraft, a wonderful mission,
and our final pass by Titan.
I worked on the Cassini
mission for over 30 years,
and that's the time
it takes Saturn
to circle the sun a single time.
And when you work on a mission
for that long of a time,
and when you work for people,
many of whom stayed and
were there as long as I was,
you really start to
feel like family.
You get to know each other.
You take vacations together.
You attend meetings together.
You see your families
grow up together.
And then when the
mission ends, it's hard,
because you know you'll keep
in touch with this family,
these people who
feel like friends.
And yet you also know you'll
go your separate ways.
- So for the people who
have been with the team
from the beginning, thank you.
And I hope you found
that you are now
30 year wiser and smarter,
and it has been a
great experience.
But for the people
who joined later,
hopefully you found that
also a great stepping stone,
and great experience
for you guys
to lead the future of
planetary exploration.
So thank you, again.
- Cheers.
- Where are the cookies?
- [Narrator] The next
day, Cassini engineers
gather for their last in
flight operations meeting.
- 5502 is when we predict
to hit 100% duty cycle.
And AACS predicts loss of
signal 12 seconds after that.
Navigation, Dwayne.
- [Dwayne] As of yesterday, at
about 1:30 in the afternoon,
we had our last Titan flyby.
And we're on our
way into Saturn now.
- [Chairman] DSN, Mike.
- So we had seven
passes last week,
14 command files, including
the last set of builds.
We have no more
commanding for real time.
- One-on-one, Jan.
- Okay, the spacecraft's
basically nominal.
We have no new ISAs,
no other errors.
And then basically we've
got the end of the sequence.
We're just clocking out.
Here we are, and knowing that
this is the end, is very sad.
But knowing in a
mission like Cassini,
where we had an ending date,
we had a sequence of events to
follow, gave us some purpose.
All the team stepped up.
I'm very grateful
for all your support.
And just want to say, thank you.
- Does anyone else
have anything?
- Ah, yeah.
Just because everyone else has
piled on with the thank yous,
you, here in the room,
and out on the phone,
have rocked the world.
And this is our last
meeting with the spacecraft.
But it has just been
an incredible ride.
I am very, very proud
to have been associated
with all of you.
And as an incentive
for next meeting,
when we don't have a spacecraft,
we will bring donuts.
Thanks, everyone.
(all clapping)
(voices overlapping)
- And now already,
there's two hours.
- Two hours.
- Two hours and counting.
- It is now 2:55 in the
morning in California.
We got about two hours
to go until the end.
Science data on the
recorders are done.
We're currently in a real
time plunge configuration.
So everything now is
essentially real time data
from the instruments, as
we go into the planet.
The FFTs will begin
to fade and decrease.
And then, at just one point,
they'll just disappear entirely
and that'll be the end.
That'll be the end.
(contemplative music)
- Oh, Lord. What
do we got up here?
It's really hard to end
the mission this way.
This one's been my companion,
constant companion,
for 22 years.
My job has always been,
take care of the spacecraft.
Everything's working
just perfectly.
I mean, you have to
recognize the fact
that we're out of propellant.
But I have no idea
how I'm gonna feel.
- Look, this is
my screen up here.
So this screen here
is the last 10 minutes
of the one up at the top.
The one at the top is
kind of the big picture.
And this one has
atmosphere models.
This is also the
last 10 minutes,
but this one does not
have atmosphere models.
So what we're gonna,
what we're hoping to see
when we get to the very end
and get into the atmosphere,
is this one's gonna start
being different from this one.
Right now they
look very similar.
Once this one starts
changing from this one,
then we know that we're
in the atmosphere,
and we're experiencing
drag on the spacecraft.
- About a minute
before loss of signal.
The other spot we've got over
at the attitude control system.
Those charts on the
right of that screen
are showing thruster activity.
And we're gonna watch those
just go right up the
walls, so to speak.
And again for about a minute.
I mean everything happens
so fast right now.
- So what we're seeing
is each of these little
places where the
curve turns around
is where the
thrusters are firing.
We're trying to control the
orientation of the spacecraft.
And every time we see a
little change of direction,
that's a truster pulse.
And those pulses are getting
more and more frequent.
And the reason for that is
we're getting closer to Saturn,
and its gravity
gradient is starting
to rotate the spacecraft around.
What's gonna happen
is eventually,
instead of balancing
slowly along the edge,
it's just gonna be
sitting right on the edge,
firing the thrusters
continuously,
all the way up to
the point where
the thrusters are on fully,
and it can no longer
maintain that attitude.
And then it'll just drift
outside of our thresholds.
And then we'll be tumbling,
and that will be the end of it.
(dramatic music)
- When do we want to tear up
the ceremonial anomaly plan?
(all clapping)
- [Scientist] Yes, if you
think of Cassini as a symphony,
this is the final,
final movement.
There's so many emotions.
I mean, it's such a great
sweet ride it's been.
It's been a triumph.
- [Scientist] We are a village.
It has been a
phenomenal teamwork.
We finish each other's
sentences. We tie
each other's shoes.
It is absolutely gonna
be something that I will
never be able to recreate,
and I will miss it greatly.
- [Narrator] Among those
arriving is Mike Watkins.
- Wish these were not always
at 3:00 am and 5:00 am.
- [Scientist] Were you able
to get any sleep before this?
- Couple hours, a little bit.
- [Narrator] Watkins is
one year into leading JPL,
the fourth JPL Director
Cassini has seen.
(dramatic music)
- Hello everyone,
I'm Gay Yee Hill.
And welcome to NASA's Jet
Propulsion Laboratory.
After three decades in
space, the Cassini spacecraft
has reached the end of
its journey at Saturn.
The spacecraft made its final
approach to the giant planet.
Meanwhile, it is 4:00
am here in California.
The sun is not up yet,
and more than 1500
Cassini scientists,
engineers, alumni,
friends and family
have gathered for this moment.
How does it feel,
Todd, to be here?
- Hi, Gay. Well, it's
great to be back.
As you and I sat there in 2004,
we never dreamt we'd
be here in 2017,
still talking about Cassini,
and collecting science data.
So I'm just thrilled to be here,
even having aged
some years since SOI.
- [Systems Lead] Flight
Director, Systems Lead.
- [Flight Director] Go ahead.
- [Systems Lead] All
subsystems are nominal.
We are go for a final plunge.
- [Flight Director] Copy.
- [Mission Planning] The
spacecraft has just crossed
40 degrees North latitude
- [Flight Director]
Copy, thank you.
- The trajectory is the
very latest trajectory that
we've reconstructed with the
latest data that we could get.
So that little dot
here, that's Cassini.
So it's pretty accurate.
And, yeah.
That's cool.
- [Mission Planning] Systems
Lead, Mission Planning.
- [Systems Lead] Go
ahead, Mission Planning.
- [Mission Planning]
Spacecraft has just crossed
30 degrees North latitude,
altitude is 6,000 miles.
[Systems Lead] Copy, thank you.
- Miles.
- Yeah, they're calling
out miles. That's weird.
- Yeah.
- [Zahi] Yeah, we
usually don't use them.
- We've never used miles.
- Well, we are a little
over 10 minutes away
from the loss of signal.
So we will be focusing
our attention to
the control room very soon now.
But before we do, let's
take a moment to chat
with JPL Director, Mike Watkins.
So Mike, how are you feeling?
- Well, first good morning.
- [Gay] Yeah, a
very early morning.
- We always tend
to do these events
somehow at three in the
morning or five in the morning.
- [Gay] Why do we do that?
But it's kind of a bittersweet
event for all of us, I think.
For me personally, it's
more sweet than bitter,
because Cassini has been
such a fantastic mission.
But I think one of the important
things about these events
is to celebrate the
incredible hard work,
the decades of hard
work of the team
that designed, built,
and operated Cassini.
And that's really, the
heart of the spacecraft
is really the people
that worked on it,
and the people that
have been operating it.
And this is a great
time to celebrate those,
that level of dedication,
that devotion.
To work on something
for 10, 20, 30 years,
that's sort of unparalleled
in human history.
(calm music)
- [AECS] Systems,
this is AECS one.
[Systems Lead] Go ahead, AECS.
- [AECS] We're still
waiting for transition
to high rate mode,
but it looks like
we're gonna start
accumulating thruster on time,
at a higher rate now.
And our attitude control error
is starting to be more active.
[Systems Lead] Copy.
- [AECS] And we are
in the atmosphere.
[Systems Lead] Copy, thank you.
(dramatic music)
- Here we go.
- Oh yeah, there it is.
(voices overlapping)
(dramatic music)
- Flight Director,
Radio Science.
we have loss of signal at
X band, and sierra band.
(dramatic music)
(music stops)
- [Flight Director] Project
Manager, Flight Director.
- [Project Manager] Go ahead.
- [Flight Director] Okay,
we call loss of signal,
one one, five five, four
six, for the S-band,
so that would be the
end of the spacecraft.
- Project Manager on FSO chord.
I hope you're all
as deeply proud
of this amazing accomplishment.
Congratulations to you all.
This has been an
incredible mission,
an incredible spacecraft.
And you're all an
incredible team.
I'm gonna call this
the end of mission.
Project manager off the net.
(all clapping)
(contemplative music)
- My feeling was, I
want to hug somebody,
and share saying goodbye.
And that that was hard. It
was hard to say goodbye.
- [Scientist] And seven-four,
if you're listening,
Project Manager or Program
Manager has confirmed
end of mission at one
one, five five, four six.
This concludes Cassini's
13 year exploration
of the Saturn system.
- The looks that you
see on people's faces.
We're not acting. We felt that.
You're looking at raw
emotion at that point.
I thought I was gonna
be okay, and I wasn't.
We did it, and it worked.
But it's over. Now what?
- Been doing this a long time.
- Yeah. Let's do another one.
- Yeah, let's do another one.
(laughing)
(dramatic music)
(orchestral music)
- [AECS] Maneuver
Lead, this is AECS.
- [Maneuver Lead]
AECS, go ahead.
- [AECS] The post burn
unwind roll turn is complete.
- [Maneuver Lead] Copy, thanks.
- [Flight Director] FSO chord?
- [Maneuver Lead] Flight
director, go ahead.
- [Flight Director]
Yeah, you can go ahead
and check people off net.
We'll debrief everybody
in here on the net.
And we'll walk through
what we need to do,
including what
happens with the DTUs.
- [Maneuver Lead] Okay,
copy. Go it, thank you.
- [Thermal] Maneuver
Lead, this is Thermal.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Thermal, go ahead.
- [Thermal] The thermal
devices subsystem
is nominal, following
on maneuver.
Requesting permission
to go off to the net.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Copy. Sounds good.
Thanks for your support.
- [Thermal] Copy that.
- [Maneuver Lead] Com, go ahead.
- [Com] We would like to
report that telecom is nominal.
The subsystem is nominal.
And the Doppler and
telemetry look good.
So we would request
a sign off the net.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Copy. Sounds good.
Thanks for your support.
CDS, Go ahead.
- Yeah, we note that
the CDS system is
nominal at this time, and
we'd like to sign off the net.
- [Maneuver Lead] Okay. Copy.
Thanks for your support.
- All is nominal,
and I'd like to
request permission
to get of the net.
- [Maneuver Lead] Copy, thanks.
- Maneuver Lead, System
Fault Protection.
- [Maneuver Lead] SFP, go ahead.
- I can confirm
no fault protection activity,
and all telemetry
is per predict,
as of page 10 on the procedure.
And SFP would like
permission to go off net.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Okay, copy. Thank you.
- Final status for the OTM
on our side is
about one sigma off.
Request for signing off.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Okay, copy. Thank you.
- [Scientist] I
managed the maneuver,
and I've done my final queries.
And it looks like
a nominal burn.
So I'm requesting permission
to sign off the net.
- [Maneuver Lead] Okay. Copy.
Thanks for your support.
- [Prop] Maneuver Lead, Prop.
- [Maneuver Lead]
Prop, go ahead.
- Burn time was nailed
within about half a second.
So it looks like a good RCS
burn, with respect to Prop.
- Ace, Maneuver
Lead on FSO chord.
- [Ace] Maneuver Lead, Ace.
- Yeah, so at this time all
subsystems have reported
a nominal burn for OTM 469.
So I will be signing
off as Systems Lead.
- [Ace] Copy that. Thank you.
- Thank you.
(calm music)